Operation Lighthouse
re the unsolved murder
of Gail Vella
on September 10th. 2019.
The name we've been given
is Ross Turner.
Enter the property.
Five Three.
DP for custody transfer.
bringing suspect out now.
Interview of Terry Boyle
by Detective Chief
Inspector Davidson.
Mr Boyle.
did you shoot Gail Vella?
- Did anyone see that?
- Armed police!
Drop your weapons!
A significant number
of other fingerprints
match an individual identified
by the Police National Computer
as Carl Banks.
Carl Banks has an
extensive history of violence.
including firearms offences.
The person who made me see that
there was another way. to be
a useful member of society.
was a police officer.
He's the reason why
I wanted to become
a police officer too.
To help people.
I can't share any details.
but we might be looking
into Vella.
Great. So. either
I'm accused of being a traitor
or I become one
to avoid being accused?
We really can't be sure about
the loyalty
of some of these people.
They could banjax
the whole thing.
I sent a photo to the Handler.
He confirms it's the CHIS.
You're not suggesting
Davidson was involved?
You have no idea
what she's capable of.
It's over.
How come
I've never met your family?
I don't have one.
I've released him
without charge.
No way am I going after
someone like Terry Boyle
because he's the easy way out.
Boss. is everything okay?
- I should. er...
- Yeah.
Sir.
Skipper...
Good Morning.
Thank you as you were.
As you were.
I have authorised
an official AC-12 inquiry
into Operation Lighthouse.
Gail Vella's murder
is this force's highest
profile investigation.
It will be our job to detect
whether police misconduct
and/or corruption
has contributed to this murder
remaining unsolved.
- DS Arnott.
- Sir.
SIO on Lighthouse
is Detective Chief Inspector
Joanne Davidson.
No MIT officers are aware
AC-12 is scrutinising
Lighthouse.
All information
we've harvested so far
has been acquired from a source
on The Hill known as Officer J.
...to our inquiry.
- The CHIS's name
was Alastair Oldroyd. - 22.
Oldroyd was in a pub
on the night of October 26th
when the person
calling himself Ross Turner
gave Oldroyd homophobic abuse.
Turner intimidated Oldroyd
by allegedly boasting
of involvement
in Gail Vella's murder.
Sorry. sir.
- have you got a sec?
- Come in.
You don't need me to tell you
we need a witness
to this meeting
between Oldroyd and Turner
to identify whether
it was Boyle or Banks.
Unfortunately. the CHIS lied
about the name of the pub.
Handler believes
he was protecting friends
who trade drugs there.
We're checking out
establishments in the vicinity
of Beechwood House
for CCTV plus Local Authority
cameras in the area
just in the hope
of identifying Oldroyd.
Banks or Boyle
on the night of the 26th.
- Cheers. Chris. crack on.
- Boss.
- Thanks.
- Ma'am.
Boss. obviously
we've got to consider
whether Oldroyd's death
was suicide or murder...
Hence. we're investigating it.
Yeah. I'm not saying anything
you don't know already. boss.
but if it was murder
then it raises the question
that someone knew Oldroyd
had info
on Gail Vella's death.
I know.
Hate to say it. Kate.
but one thing I've learned
over the years.
the fewer coppers
in the loop. the better.
What's going on
with Farida Jatri?
I was about to ask the same.
sir.
She's just handed
in a transfer request.
"Personal reasons."
She's an experienced PS.
We're at a crucial phase
of Vella.
In confidence. sir.
I've noticed some issues
with PS Jatri.
What kind of issues?
I don't want to say anything
that might come back
to haunt us.
Last thing you need's
a tribunal.
What?
I'll draft a glowing reference
and she'll be
some other station's problem.
You're a lifesaver.
Yeah.
- Sir.
- What have you got?
Sir. the team have managed
to pull
some Gail Vella reports
from our archive.
Obviously they all relate
to cases involving AC-12.
- Chief Inspector...
- Chief Inspector Osbourne!
I take pride
in the courage
and professionalism
of my counterterrorism officers.
To say any more risks
prejudicing the inquest.
Thank you.
Official police statements
record
Counter Terrorism Officers
shouted "Armed Police"
and ordered Mr Ali to surrender.
Mr Ali's widow Aaliyah
insists there was no warning.
no chance to surrender.
before her husband
was gunned down
by a hail of bullets.
They lied through their teeth.
every single one of them.
except you. Steve.
I mean. talk about an outrage.
the commanding officer.
made Chief.
If that had happened
on my patch...
Jesus.
Next one. Chloe.
A jury found Retired
Chief Superintendent
Patrick Fairbank
guilty of all charges.
What that jury didn't hear
and only now
am I allowed to report
are allegations Patrick Fairbank
suppressed police investigations
into child sexual exploitation
that transcended
local political figures
such as Councillor Dale Roach.
It's now a matter
of public record
that Jimmy Savile
cultivated relationships
with senior police officers.
Savile exploited
those relationships
to intimidate anyone
attempting to investigate
his offending.
We now realise
what Savile was getting
out of those relationships
with senior police officers.
What remains unknown.
and uninvestigated.
is what those officers
were getting
out of their relationship
with Savile.
Gail Vella reporting
from Queen Elizabeth Law Courts.
Sir. Gail Vella drew attention
to alleged links
between organised crime.
politicians and senior police officers
and these are just the reports
we found in our own archive.
Wee girl killed in cold blood.
Or a killer. free as a bird.
- Thank you. Chloe.
- Sir.
- Cheers. Chloe.
- Sarge.
Gaffer. it can't be
a coincidence
Carl Banks
was a violent offender
involved with organised crime.
Yeah. but if your man
pulled the trigger.
that means he's a gun for hire.
That order came from higher up.
But the question still remains
what is the motive
for Gail Vella's murder?
All right. she's
a controversial journalist.
I'll give you that.
but there's no evidence
to suggest
that she dug up anything
that wasn't there before.
Maybe she was working
on something that would...
Superintendent Hastings.
Thanks Steve. Thanks.
Sir.
Yes. I'll be right down.
Steph. what are you doing here?
You promised
you'd call me back. It's HMRC.
Not here. not here.
let's go somewhere private.
- Tea. coffee?
- We're fine.
- Thanks though.
- Cool.
- So. have a seat.
- Yes.
How can I help you?
We'd like to ask you some
questions about Gail Vella.
You were working
with her closely
at the time of her death?
Detectives interviewed me
a few days after.
Our department is conducting
further inquiries.
Yeah. I was her producer
for a couple of years.
One line of inquiry
is she fell victim
to an obsessed fan.
Do you recall any individuals
that gave Gail
cause for concern?
Female journalists
get the worst of it.
From accusations of bias
to threats of sexual violence.
Everything was reported
at the time
to our security
or to the police.
You say Ms Vella
received threats
as a result of her reporting.
Were there any particularly
controversial reports?
Maybe I should show you.
The Deputy Chief Constable and I
are pleased to report
that Operation Pear Tree
has completed
a thorough investigation
into institutionalised
complicity
between organised criminals
and corrupt police officers.
It's robust findings
couldn't be clearer.
There is no institutionalised
corruption
in this police force.
Operation Pear Tree.
the inquiry described as
"the most thorough"
ever undertaken
into police corruption.
is now officially closed.
Some will wonder why this news
is being announced
over a holiday weekend.
Cynics might conclude the Police
and Crime Commissioner
would prefer his statement
isn't examined too closely.
Perhaps Mr Sindwhani has learned
the secret to high office
appears no longer to reside
in revealing the deepest truths.
but in telling
the most attractive lies.
Gail Vella reporting...
I had to cut that
from the broadcast version.
This unbroadcast material.
it would never
have been released?
Not in this form. no.
She'd seen the success
of a podcast
about police corruption
surrounding the murder
of a private detective.
Daniel Morgan.
The material Gail
couldn't get on air.
she was funnelling into
a podcast serial of her own.
Where can we access
this podcast?
It never got that far. Gail
must not have finished it.
Do you know anything about
the content of this podcast?
I know she was pursuing
several senior police officers
for interviews.
She was digging
much more deeply into why
there'd been suppression
of police inquiries
into the likes
of Councillor Dale Roach.
She keep notes or recordings?
Yes. What journalist wouldn't?
That's why I suggested
Gail's killer
must have stolen them.
Sorry? You disclosed this
to the original
murder detectives?
And they said
there was no grounds
to suspect a burglary.
This is the first
we've heard of burglary
being a factor
in Gail Vella's murder.
Nor was there evidence
of a disturbance
inside of the property.
If the killer stole something.
he knew exactly
what he was looking for
and where to find it.
I'm assuming the original
investigation
seized all of Gail Vella's
electronic devices.
Yes. sir.
They were after messages
or threats from an obsessed fan.
Yes. but they weren't looking
at her journalism.
If your theory is right. Steve.
these files could point
the finger at someone
who may have had a motive
to order her murder.
I think those devices
need to be re-analysed.
We'll have to find
a way to do that
without alerting Davidson.
Right.
Thank you. Chloe.
Sir.
You're worried about
what might happen to Kate
when Davidson finds out
we're investigating her?
- Yes. sir.
- I get it. son. I really do.
I get it. But...
Kate has made her bed.
Now she's got to lie in it.
And we've a job to do.
Sir.
Wait. Steve.
I've been giving the situation
some thought.
And loyalty works both ways.
I'm gonna have to confirm it
with HR
but ahead of the formal
promotion process.
I am making you a Temp DI.
Congratulations. son.
you've earned it.
Thank you. sir.
All right.
Just like old times.
Yeah.
We're moving forward with Vella.
Moving forward how?
At some point we're gonna hit
the Hill.
Shit. for Christ sake. Steve.
This is why I got you here.
I can't leave a digital trail.
But I wanted you to know.
Why are you involving me?
We've got some leads.
but look. Kate.
if you can feed me
the inside track on Davidson.
maybe we won't need
to show our hand just yet...
Christ sake. Steve.
she's me gaffer.
- you want me to rat on her?
- You're no rat if she's bent.
- What am I then?
- An honest copper.
Oh yeah. I'm sure
everyone'll see it like that.
Look. Kate.
it goes beyond Davidson.
If organised crime ordered
the murder of Gail Vella.
they're protecting Carl Banks
and framing Terry Boyle.
Yeah. we get it.
We're working on it.
Look. I just need to know when.
When is it going
to come out that AC-12
are investigating Davidson?
I've already said too much.
Yeah. likewise.
You always chose
a right shithole.
All right. Chris.
Pathologist's
in there now. boss.
Knife wound to the throat.
Looks like the body's
been here for a few days.
Witnesses?
This is a long derelict site
with no security presence
and no CCTV.
Highly unlikely we'll harvest
any surveillance images.
Any ID yet?
Matches the appearance
of Carl Banks.
Shit.
Good news. ma'am.
The search team's found a knife.
No apparent blood
deposits on the ground.
The Best test for them anyway.
The killer didn't put
much effort
into evidence disposal.
DI Fleming.
Farida's replacement.
- PC Ryan...
- Pilkington. ma'am.
Pleased to meet you. ma'am.
Don't knock it. Kate.
We're overdue a lucky break.
- Thanks. Ryan.
- Ma'am.
Fingerprints were only
a 90% match
due to early decomposition
but DNA's confirmed
the body is definitely
Carl Banks.
Sorry. ma'am.
you asked to receive
the forensic report
- as soon as it was in.
- Thanks. Ryan.
You couldn't do us a cuppa.
could you? I'm gasping.
Yeah. No problem at all. ma'am.
- DI Fleming. DS Lomax?
- I'm fine. ta.
Me too but this has been
bugging me.
have we worked together before?
Did you come and give a talk
at Training College. ma'am?
No.
- Thanks. Ryan.
- Ma'am.
Christ sake.
Boss?
Fingerprints on the knife
found close to Carl Banks's
body match Alastair Oldroyd.
The CHIS.
The pathologist confirmed
Banks died
a couple of days earlier.
The timeline works
for Oldroyd
to have killed Banks.
Yeah.
Sarge.
Err. I mean Sir.
- Shit. Sir.
- What have you got?
Sir. it's just come up
on the Box.
Carl Banks has been found dead.
No more beating about the bush.
- We raid Operation Lighthouse.
- Sir.
I'll put together a team
and transport.
AC-12. DI Arnott.
It's your lawful duty
to comply with my officers.
Sir.
DI Arnott. AC-12.
We have the lawful
authority to investigate
Operation Lighthouse.
All officers go to your desks.
You'll each be questioned
by an AC-12 case worker.
You'll each be obliged
to surrender all materials
relating to Operation Lighthouse
to said case workers.
Failure to comply will be
a breach of your Duties
and Responsibilities under
Police Conduct Regulations
and may lead
to a misconduct charge
- under said regulations.
- Nobody move.
What the hell's all this about?
- On whose authority?
- We have a signed authority
from Deputy Chief
Constable Wise to seize
all MIT files relating
to the murder of Gail Vella.
Let me see that.
Sir. as you know.
willful obstruction
of my officers executing
their lawful duty
- is a criminal offence.
- DCI Davidson.
I notified the DCC
of my concerns regarding
leaking of confidential
police information
such as the operation
to arrest Ross Turner
and the identity of the CHIS
who gave us Turner's name
and address.
The DCC agreed to a moratorium
on further distribution
of Operation Lighthouse files
until said information leakage
has been fully investigated.
We'd be the ones
to investigate it!
Nonetheless you'll see
the DCC's authorised me
to withhold Operation
Lighthouse files.
Why didn't the DCC
inform us about this?
To prevent information
leakage. naturally.
No. he did it
to make mugs of AC-12.
That was just an added bonus.
- Priceless!
- Let's go.
Right. everyone. let's go.
Cheers. Kate. nice one.
How did Davidson know?
Give me a minute.
Steve. I'm sorry.
I trusted you. mate.
Look. I'm damned if I do.
I'm damned if I don't.
What was I supposed to do?
Andrea advised me this is
about Operation Lighthouse.
I need to be in the loop.
Well. I am here because AC-12's
lawful investigation
has been unjustly obstructed.
Operation Lighthouse
has had its setbacks of course
but your involvement
needs to be correctly handled
so the public don't leap
to the wrong conclusion.
I've briefed Andrea
on the required optics.
This isn't an inquiry
into misconduct
slash corruption.
Well. the investigation
usually precedes the findings.
Clearly. we're all frustrated
Gail Vella's murderer hasn't
been brought to justice yet.
so it makes sense to pitch
AC-12's involvement
as a routine performance review.
Officers of your rank
normally appreciate politics
as much as policing.
Yes.
I'm interested in one thing
and one thing only.
And that's bent coppers.
I hope you'll cooperate.
Superintendent.
Now. apologies.
if you'll excuse me.
I'm due to attend
the Crime Executive.
Sir.
Unless there are
any outstanding issues. Ted.
I'm prepared to reissue
the authority for AC-12
to proceed with your review
of Operation Lighthouse.
It appears my team
have been delayed
for nothing better
than a PR briefing.
the result of which
is that MIT officers
are now aware of our inquiry
and may be concealing evidence
as we speak!
No one's concealing evidence.
Ted.
They're working their
bollocks off
trying to find
Gail Vella's killer.
Ma'am.
How'd it go. sir?
Well. We're back in business.
Thank you. sir.
So. you make the mess
and I tidy it up.
is that how this goes?
Well. you're not denying it
so it must have been Officer J.
Or DI Kate Fleming
who blew the gaff.
I reckon you'd only trust Kate
with that kind of information.
yeah?
Well. she's cooked
her goose now.
God help her if she thinks
she's gonna get
some kind of special treatment
from me.
because she's got
another thing coming.
As for DCI Davidson.
she must have had
great fun pulling this stroke.
But she will be laughing
on the other side of her face
when I'm finished with her.
Serve her with a Reg 15.
- Sir.
- Carry on.
DC Bishop. AC-12.
I'm sure you can all guess
what this is about.
I need access to your computer.
Could you stand up. please.
Show me your files. please.
Can I have your passwords.
please.
I need your login details.
What is this document here?
Here you go. sir.
Ma'am. please find enclosed
a Regulation 15 notice
requiring you to attend
AC-12 for a formal interview
within the next 10 working days.
A copy of this letter
has been sent
to your Police Federation
Representative.
- Steve?
- I was up on a case.
I'm sorry. Steph.
I should've called.
No. no. it's fine. come in.
- Tea. isn't it?
- Yeah. Ta.
How are the girls?
Gemma still doesn't get it.
not really.
I'm dreading her
not remembering her daddy.
These'll help.
John won't be forgotten.
Thanks for all you did
at the time.
You didn't have to.
I'd like to think he'd
have done the same for me.
He died in the line of duty.
Shame the big bosses
never saw it that way.
Sorry. I ought to know.
milk and sugar?
Just milk. please.
It's good you were able
to keep the house.
I know you were worried.
Tearing me hair out more like.
Fortunately. there was
John's life insurance.
Nice TV.
Champions' League game's
on later.
Not that you lot've got
an interest.
Next season.
I didn't know you'd bother
with the sports channels.
It all comes in a package.
Cheap as chips.
Sorry. what am I like? Sit down.
Steve?
It's just a spasm. It'll pass.
You sure?
I've got some painkillers
in the car.
Don't move. I'll get them.
I'll get your car keys.
Inside pocket.
I can't believe the DCC
caved so easily.
Sorry. boss.
Not your fault at all.
Thanks for the heads-up.
I know the kind of cases
that AC-12 are into. boss.
Out of work. forget "Boss".
You all right?
- This Reg 15...
- Yeah.
I know how it must feel.
but it's just the way
AC-12 operate.
Truth is.
it's all getting a bit tense.
How's it make me look.
investigating a guy
with learning difficulties...
Straight up. Jo.
do you think
he could have killed Gail?
You've been doing this job
long enough
to realise we can never know
for sure.
We just gather the evidence.
do our best.
And right now.
my best is nowhere near
good enough.
A young woman...
could've been you or me. Kate.
her life cut short.
And whoever did
it's got away with it.
and that's my fault.
Do you fancy another?
Ladies.
Two more. please.
Can we get those?
Have a good night. guys.
- Two more. please.
- Certainly.
I'm sorry. Kate.
my self-pity's
blown your chances.
Na. not really my type.
You sure you're okay to drive?
Yes. Sorry about all that
earlier. I'm fine.
Last thing I meant
was to put you out.
Gerraway. it was nice
to have some grownup company
for a change.
This a long job?
The case you're up here on?
Could be.
If you're passing again.
don't hesitate.
Don't stay out. it's freezing.
I've got to set the sat nav
and everything.
Night. Steve. safe journey.
Night.
Thanks for coming out. Kate.
Sorry to unload my problems.
No worries. glad I could be
a sounding board.
Well. this is me.
It's Mark's turn
to have Josh this weekend.
If you're at a loose end...
I need to check my diary.
Yeah. No pressure.
My diary's empty.
I've just come out
of a long-term relationship.
I. uh...
It would be nice
to see you at the weekend.
Chloe. how's it going?
Davidson gave us
full cooperation.
So we got the lot.
We've recovered
Vella's computers
that were seized
straight after her murder.
I thought you'd want
to prioritise them.
- Great. Hi. Amanda.
- Hi.
The Digital Forensics Team
have triaged
the desk-top computer.
the lap-top computer.
The truth is.
they're remarkably clean.
What do you mean?
All applications
still had store settings.
Hardly any personal files.
Well they were planted.
Her killer replaced
her actual computers
to cover up the burglary.
I'll order
the keyboards to be swabbed
and screens fingerprinted
that way we can see
if Gail ever even touched them.
Good call. So.
you've found nothing at all?
The only item of interest
is a tiny audio file.
It appears
only partially downloaded.
- How would that happen?
- Going with your theory.
it would be
when the murderer installed
the replacement devices.
They would have synced
to her phone momentarily.
started to import the audio file
before the murderer
broke the link.
That would involve him
knowing her passwords.
Sorry.
...Savile lied to cover them up.
Some police officers
not only accepted those lies.
They propagated them.
We're losing our power
to challenge lies.
There's some people
you can't challenge.
Okay. So.
we're losing our power
to challenge lies.
There's some people
you can't challenge.
Sorry. sir.
I didn't think
you'd still be here.
We need to find
the rest of Gail's recordings.
Yeah. Amanda said she's on it.
D'you mind me asking. sir.
but why have these been put up?
The Gaffer's never
going to give it up.
not as long as he still runs
this place.
- And what about you?
- What about me?
Well. do you still believe
there's a fourth man
out there? H?
I've moved on.
That's us now.
Anticorruption Unit 12 interview
of Detective Chief Inspector
Joanne Davidson
in the presence of her Police
Federation Representative
DCI John Rix
by Superintendent Hastings.
Detective Inspector Arnott.
and Detective Constable Bishop.
Ma'am. this interview relates
to Operation Lighthouse.
the inquiry into the murder
of Gail Vella
on September 10th. 2019.
on which you've been
Senior Investigating Officer
since 6th of October
of that same year.
Document 6 in your folders.
Document 6 is a copy
of an incident report
lawfully seized by AC-12
from the offices
of the Murder Investigation Team
located at Hillside Lane
Police Station
on the 4th of November.
Said incident report
describes events
on the morning of 27th October.
specifically the diversion
and delay of an operation
to arrest a suspect
in the murder of Gail Vella
in order to attend
an Armed Robbery taking place
at Hickey's Bookmakers.
Verlaine Road.
On screen. Images 11 to 14.
Images 11 to 14 show
street views of said location.
DCI Davidson.
can you kindly explain
your actions
on the morning of October 27th
in relation
to this Armed Robbery.
En route to arrest the suspect.
I observed a suspicious vehicle.
further inquiries detected
an armed robbery in progress.
I ordered my officers
to intervene.
DCI Davidson's actions
prevented a serious
and immediate threat
to members of the public.
Commendable.
DI Arnott.
Image 14 on screen.
Image 14 shows the line of sight
from the route of the MIT convoy
to the location
of the suspicious vehicle.
Given you were
a front-facing passenger.
it was a narrow line of sight.
And plus. you were going
like the clappers.
Nonetheless.
I did see the vehicle.
and as a result.
numerous members of the public
were saved
from a terrifying ordeal.
Oh.
And what was it about
this vehicle?
- Sir?
- I mean.
it's just an ordinary van
parked in an ordinary street.
Why give it the time of day?
A registration check
proved suspicious.
Yes. but you only found that out
after you stopped
to investigate.
It was an idling MPV
parked adjacent
to a bookmakers.
The driver wasn't reading
a newspaper
or messing about on his phone.
His eyes were fixed
on the bookies.
He was alert
for a quick getaway.
And you deduced all that
in the fraction of a second?
Call it a police officer's
instinct.
Oh. yes. we all get those.
from time-to-time DCI Davidson.
I might be getting one
right now.
DC Bishop.
We've examined MIT records
in relation
to the Armed Robbery.
Document 12 in your folders
and Image 20 on screen.
Image 20 shows the men
arrested in the act
of conducting an Armed Robbery
of Hickey's Bookmakers
on the 27th of October.
None of these men has a history
of serious or violent crime.
The robbery took place
early in the morning
when takings
would be at their lowest.
So. what would you deduce
from these facts. DCI Davidson?
A group of amateur criminals
attempted an armed robbery
in an amateur fashion.
According
to Murder Investigation Team
files lawfully seized
on the 4th of November.
attending the Armed Robbery
on the morning
of the 27th of October
caused a delay
of two hours
and twenty-five minutes
to the operation
planned to arrest a suspect
using the alias Ross Turner
believed to reside
-at Flat 4
-F. Beechwood House.
Moss Heath.
This delay was out
of DCI Davidson's control.
One of the Armed Robbers
was shot dead
by an Authorised
Firearms Officer.
This necessitated
a forensic deployment
and replacement AFOs.
We also understand
that an authority
for Directed Surveillance
applied to Beechwood House.
The required authority
should have been
for Intrusive Surveillance.
As a result.
while the matter was resolved.
surveillance was absent
for a period
of three hours
and thirty-five minutes.
It needed to be resolved.
Any evidence captured
during the wrong authority
would've been inadmissible.
Yeah. Then maybe
it would've been a good idea
to get the right authority
in the first place.
wouldn't you say?
The error in assigning the wrong
surveillance authority
was committed
by a senior officer.
That isn't in the file.
I chose not to embarrass him.
Now look. DCI Davidson.
we are charged here
with investigating
serious crimes.
not least the murder
of a young woman
in the prime of her life.
and I expect
all policemen and women
to uphold their duty
to the public
above any misguided loyalty
they may have
to their fellow officers.
Now who was the senior officer?
No comment. sir.
DI Arnott will you bookmark
that for the DIR:
failure to comply.
Sir.
DC Bishop.
Image 29 on screen.
Please refer to Document 15
in your folders.
a copy of an arrest report
lawfully seized
on the 4th of November.
Said arrest report
describes the arrest
on the 27th of October
-at flat 4
-F. Beechwood House
of a person later
identified as Terry Boyle.
shown on the right in Image 29.
Also detected at the property
were fingerprints
and DNA deposits
matching Carl Banks.
shown on the left in Image 29.
Let's start with Terry Boyle.
According to files
lawfully seized
on November 4th.
a Covert
Human Intelligence Source
submitted information
to his Handler
which was communicated to
the Murder Investigation Team
via a phone call at 23:21
on the 26th October.
The CHIS claimed a person
using the name Ross Turner
had confessed
to the murder of Gail Vella.
Terry Boyle's semen
was detected on images
of Gail Vella found
in his permanent residence
which is located
a short distance
from Gail Vella's home.
Also detected at the property
were chemical traces
of heroin and cocaine and.
on an item of outer clothing.
particles of gunshot residue.
Incriminating evidence.
Gail Vella's Peugeot 108
was intercepted.
As Ms Vella got out
of the vehicle.
she was murdered
with a single gunshot
carried out
using a hard-contact method
in which the muzzle
of the pistol was forced
against the back
of Ms Vella's head.
This technique confines noise
and gunshot powder.
The murderer successfully evaded
all neighbourhood
security cameras.
These findings strongly
suggest a contract killing
of the type
ordered by organised crime.
Terry Boyle
has no criminal record.
no known association
with organised crime.
and suffers
from learning difficulties
which raise doubts
regarding his capacity
to commit a cold-blooded
assassination.
The finding of images
of Gail Vella suggested Boyle
was an obsessed fan.
While the hard-contact
technique is associated
with contract killing.
it's not exclusive.
There's no physical reason
an amateur
couldn't do the same.
The particles of gunshot residue
also link Boyle to the crime.
Well they're below
the threshold amount
you'd expect if Boyle
had been holding the gun.
then add in the total lack
of blood spatter.
there's not even a spot.
That's correct. DI Arnott.
We suspect the coat
was cross contaminated
from Boyle's hands
or other clothing.
clothing he could've disposed
of after the murder.
That's speculation. ma'am.
You've got no evidence.
Which is why
I didn't charge him.
Right. let's take a look
at this fella Carl Banks.
Image 30 on screen.
Image 30 shows
Carl Banks' criminal record.
Banks has a long association
with organised crime
and a history of violence.
including firearms offences.
Now he fits the profile
of a contract killer.
To use your words. DI Arnott.
"that's speculation."
Also. there's the question
of motive.
Terry Boyle fits the profile
of an obsessed fan.
We've never been able
to identify a motive
for a contract killing
against Gail Vella.
But there's the possibility
Vella was working
on an explosive story.
not only was she executed.
her research was stolen.
A desk-top and lap-top computer
recovered from the property
and recently re-examined
bear no fingerprints
or DNA deposits
matching Gail Vella.
We believe these items
were planted
to conceal a burglary.
That's not in our files.
No. But it's in ours.
We're detectives too. you know.
In case you hadn't noticed.
DCI Davidson has led
an exemplary inquiry.
If you've got new information.
you should share it
with the
Murder Investigation Team.
According to your files.
fingerprints and DNA deposits
matching Banks detected
at Beechwood House
were far more numerous
than those matching Boyle.
suggesting Banks
was the primary resident.
And also detected
at Beechwood House
were signs of forced entry.
Image 37 on screen
is from Carl Banks's postmortem.
Document 21 in your folders
is a copy
of the postmortem report.
According to said postmortem report.
the pathologist concluded
Carl Banks died
from exsanguination due
to a deep laceration
to the neck most likely
inflicted by a knife.
Also detected on Banks's body
were lacerations and bruising
caused by heavy blunt trauma
to the head.
facial lacerations and bruising.
and lesions on both wrists
consistent with ligature restraints.
All these injuries
were caused some time
before his death.
And time of death
was put at on or around
the 27th of October.
So. what we have here
is forced entry
into Carl Banks's flat.
Banks beaten unconscious.
His hands tied.
And sometime
later his throat cut.
None of this could've occurred
without his arrest being delayed
and the surveillance being
absent.
Now call me suspicious.
DCI Davidson.
but it seems to me
that somebody got wind
that Banks was shooting
his mouth off
about Vella's murder
and they decided
to murder him
to stop him talking.
Not only that. that they knew...
your team was on course
to arrest him.
they knew the route
you were taking.
And to top it all.
they knew the surveillance
was absent
so that meant.
they could walk in there.
drag Banks out
and substitute him
with Terry Boyle.
And none of this. none of this.
could've happened without you.
and you alone.
spotting that van
outside the bookies
and deciding for some reason
I cannot fathom
that it warranted investigation.
Sir. all this is circumstantial.
There's no evidence to support
anyone "knowing"
any details
of Operation Lighthouse.
Evidence?
We'll give you evidence.
DC Bishop.
Image 41.
Image 41 shows
item reference AR-6.
A knife that was detected
in the vicinity
- of Carl Banks's body.
- Yes. the killer.
he didn't even bother to throw
the knife into the canal.
I mean. he left it laying around
for the search team to find.
That was handy. wasn't it.
Criminals make mistakes.
That's how we catch them.
I could say exactly the same.
DCI Davidson.
exactly the same.
Please refer to
Document 23 in your folders.
a copy of a forensic report
on item reference AR-6.
"Blood detected on AR-6
was subjected to DNA analysis.
"The DNA harvested
from blood cells on AR-6
"match with 99.9 per cent
probability DNA
"from Carl Banks.
"Fingerprints on AR-6 match with
"99.9 per cent
probability fingerprints
"belonging to Alastair Oldroyd."
Alastair Oldroyd
was the CHIS who submitted
the original intel
that Banks had confessed
- to Vella's murder.
- So.
for some reason
Alastair Oldroyd.
no history of violent crime.
kills Banks?
The evidence proves
Oldroyd handled
the murder weapon.
We suspect Banks had been
threatening Oldroyd.
Are you trying to kid us
that Alastair Oldroyd
went in there.
beat Banks unconscious
dragged him out of his flat?
He was ten stone ringing wet!
And that's not the half of it.
not by a long chalk. DI Arnott.
Document 31.
According to your files.
Oldroyd was found dead
on the 29th of October
from a fall
from the derelict
Chapel Place Car Park.
According to said files.
due to the lack of witnesses
and security cameras
it's impossible to determine
if Oldroyd jumped
or he was pushed.
Our hypothesis
is that Oldroyd killed Banks
then committed suicide.
Yeah. your hypothesis.
so there we have it.
A series of suspicious deaths
that conveniently obliterate
a trail of evidence
that might lead us
to Gail Vella's
actual murderer.
And in the meantime.
you have that wee fella.
Terry Boyle.
on police bail.
You have failed to consider
the alternative.
That Carl Banks
murdered Gail Vella
on the orders
of organised crime.
and organised criminals
murdered Carl Banks
for his silence.
and that organised criminals
framed Alastair Oldroyd
for Banks's murder and then.
staged Oldroyd's murder
to look like a suicide.
Of course. I've considered
alternatives...
And none of this.
none of this
would have happened.
without crucial information
on police activities
being leaked to organised crime.
I agree.
Excuse me?
I agree. sir.
If your theory's correct.
the only way it could've worked
would've been
for a corrupt officer
from my team to have
leaked key information
to organised crime.
Well. as I'm sure
you're aware of.
DCI Davidson.
there's really only one way
we're gonna find out.
DCI Joanne Davidson.
you do not have to say anything.
but it may harm your defence
if you do not mention
when questioned something
you later rely on in court.
Anything you do say
may be used in evidence.
DCI Davidson.
did you leak information
on your team's operations?
No. sir. I did not.
Do you know of anyone
who did leak information?
No. sir. I do not.
I'd ask if you've examined
my communications history?
As per anticorruption powers.
we've been able to access
your work calls and emails.
Any evidence that
I've been communicating
- with an OCG?
- No. ma'am.
however. we all recognise
that such communication
is typically carried out
by unregistered
so-called burner phones.
I don't have a burner phone.
Search my address.
Search my car.
We will. ma'am.
Fine.
Are we done. sir?
No. DCI Davidson.
we are not done here.
I am not happy
with some of your answers
you've given
in this interview today.
Specifically. I am concerned
about
three unanswered questions.
one. your possible collusion
in diverting
and delaying
Carl Banks's arrest.
two. your possible collusion
in the failure to maintain
constant surveillance
on Carl Banks's flat.
and three.
your possible collusion
in leaking information
regarding items one and two.
and so therefore. DCI Davidson.
I'm going to arrest you
on suspicion
of Perverting
the Course of Justice.
DCI Davidson strenuously
denies the allegations.
You will be held here
until we can find a suitable
police custody cell.
22.
Wait.
An OCG needed time
to plan the robbery
and the abduction of Banks.
If I was SIO on this.
the first thing
I'd want to know is who knew
about Banks's confession
early enough.
In order.
that's the CHIS Handler.
then my officers
who received his call.
PS Jatri and DS Lomax.
then me. then my boss.
Detective Superintendent
Buckells.
If you're going to search
my home.
I'd suggest
you search theirs too.
Do you understand
how much work I've got to do?
Right. when the Chief Super
phones up and asks
what's going on
with Lighthouse. right.
- what am I gonna tell him?
- Cheers guys.
Oh. about bloody time.
You gonna tell me
what the hell's going on?
Detective
Superintendent Buckells.
in connection
with our lawful inquiry
into Operation Lighthouse.
we have received authority
to examine
the communications activity
of certain named officers.
- Is this a piss-take or what?
- Sir. your work
and personal communications
records
are currently being scrutinised.
Furthermore.
we have received authority
to carry out a search
of your vehicle
and your home
under warrant powers.
This is a joke.
a total pigging joke.
Well. yeah. I'll tell you what.
when you find my stash
of jazz mags.
feel free to knock one out.
Thank you
for your cooperation. sir.
DI Arnott.
It's Chloe. sir.
Look. I'm at the search
and the FIs have found
a cache of burner phones.
Where? Davidson's?
No. Officer J.'s.
At Farida's.
On my way.
For the DIR.
I am showing PS Jatri
item reference CB-4.
CB-4 is an unregistered
mobile phone detected
during a lawful search
of 29 Stalton Drive.
Do you recognise this phone?
No!
For the DIR. I am showing
PS Jatri Image 76.
Image 76 shows a cache
of similar devices detected
during said lawful search
of 29 Stalton Drive.
How do you account
for these devices being found
- hidden in your home?
- They've been put there!
I don't know anything
about them!
All these devices
bear DNA deposits
matching your elimination samples.
I've never even seen them before
let alone touched them!
Examination of mobile phone CB-4
reveals calls
made in the early hours
of October 27th
to an unidentified number.
The timing of these calls
coincides exactly
with the first
intelligence report
of a suspect claiming
to have murdered Gail Vella.
Did you pass
on confidential information
on the operation
to arrest this suspect?
No! No!
I had nothing to do with it!
Farida Jatri.
I have been in consultation
with the Crown Prosecutor
and she has authorised me
to charge you
with the following offences...
- I'm being framed!
- Who's framing you?
Who are you claiming
is framing you?
It's Jo. It's Jo Davidson.
She planted those phones.
You're claiming
she broke into your house?
She didn't have to break in.
What do you mean by that?
She lived there with me.
We searched
DCI Davidson's home address.
- It appears lived in.
- Yeah.
she has her own place.
She just kept
- overnight stuff at mine.
- We found no items
belonging to another person.
She moved out.
Are you able to disclose to us
the nature of this relationship?
She was lying to me.
She lied and lied.
That's the kind
of person she is.
None of you know
what she's like...
God give me strength.
I don't know who to believe.
Well. now it seems
possible Farida
made allegations about Davidson
for personal reasons.
But the stuff we've found
since then...
Isn't enough.
Not yet anyway.
Custody.
Superintendent Hastings.
- Sir.
- Release DCI Davidson.
Sir.
FARIDA Why won't anyone
believe me?
Thanks. I'm fine from here.
Ma'am.
Where to. ma'am?
I need to pick up my car.
I don't know if they've told you
about PS Jatri...
That's what happens to a rat.
>>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org